So we do pick up today with יב. Yud Bet. We are
four lines from the top near the two dots. We've been very
fortunate that these days the סוגיאס sugyas end right at the same
break as the דף. daf. So we have just finished laying down
the foundation of the two major principles for dealing with areas of
doubt: חזקה chazakah which is status quo and רוב rov which is
majority. And in particular spoke about the question about אפשר לברר, efshar
levareir, can you rely on these when you can find out more
facts? And spoke about two types of רוב rov which is very
important for, or two types of מיעוט, mi'ut, a common and an
uncommon likelihood. And that's very important of course for what things you
have to check to make sure they're not טריפה treifa which involves
the organs. We now pick up
from four lines from the top back to the major theme of
the משנה Mishnah which is who can do the שחיטה shechitah and
when do we assume that the שחיטה shechitah is being done correctly.
So let's take a look. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב, Amar Rav
Nachman amar Rav, so Rav Nachman said in the name of Rav,
ראה אחד ששחט, ra'ah echad sheshachat,
you saw a person do a שחיטה. shechitah. אם הוא מתחילה ועד
סוף מותר לאכול משחיטתו, im hu mitchilah ve'ad sof mutar le'echol mishchitatos,
so if he's directly observed it you can eat from it, right?
The משנה Mishnah teaches even if it's a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh vekatan we assume that direct observation will tell you that everything,
will give you the full information and you'll be able to see
that it was all done correctly. ואם לאו אסור לאכול משחיטתו, ve'im
lav assur le'echol mishchitatos, and if you did not directly observe it,
you cannot eat from it. Now that's a little bizarre. Why can't
you eat from it? Who is this person that did the שחיטה?
shechitah? So that's what the גמרא Gemara wants to understand. היכי דמי?
heichi dami? What's the case? אי דידע דגמיר, ei deyada degamir, if
you know the person doing the שחיטה shechitah is knowledgeable, knows the
laws, למה לי ראו? lamah li ra'u? Why do you need to
observe him?
ואי דידע דלא גמיר, ve'ei deyada delo gamir, if you know that
the person is not knowledgeable, of course there's a middle case, you
don't know one way or the other, but right now we're talking
about the extremes. You know that he is not knowledgeable. So
ואי דידע דלא גמיר פשיטא, ve'ei deyada delo gamir peshita, obviously you
can't trust his שחיטה. shechitah. That's a point that we've been saying
all along that, I mean maybe it's not so
פשיטא, peshita, but because maybe it's somebody that has had experience, but
it's at least פשיטא peshita as far as how far we've gotten.
We've established that even experience isn't enough, somebody has to
know and if they don't know the laws, it's not good because
they might make a mistake and not realize they're making a mistake.
So if he knew the law you don't have to observe him.
If he doesn't know the laws, then obviously you have to observe
because without observing maybe he made a mistake. So what's the case?
ואלא, ve'alla, so obviously it's the middle
case, דלא ידע אי גמיר אי לא גמיר. delo yada ei gamir
ei lo gamir. Thank you. So you don't know. Meaning the, so
of course if you know he doesn't know, then it's not good
unless you observe him. But there's what about that middle case? The
case where you're not sure if he knows or not? Okay. So
he's saying if you're not sure if he knows or not, then
that's not okay. If you're not sure he knows, then it's like
knowing that he doesn't know and the only way it's good is
if you observe him. Now that is not so clear. So let's
continue.
Okay. ואי דידע דלא גמיר פשיטא ve'ei deyada delo gamir peshita that
it's not good until you observe him because as we've said before
even if he has experience, if he doesn't know the laws he
might make a mistake and not realize he's made a mistake. So
saying okay, the case is you don't know whether or not he
knows the laws. So then the גמרא Gemara says well,
ואלא דלא ידע אי גמיר אי לא גמיר. ve'ella delo yada ei
gamir ei lo gamir. So then the גמרא Gemara says okay that's
not פשיטא, peshita, but then we disagree. לימא, leima, why don't we
say the principle that we've said earlier?
רוב מצויין אצל שחיטה מומחין הן. rov metzuyin etzel shechitah mumchin hein.
If somebody שחטs shecht and we don't know whether or not they
know the laws and then he leaves. Stranger came to town, שחטed
shecht a few animals, left. Okay. We don't know whether he knew
or not. We can make an assumption and here it's very nice
that this סוגיא sugya appears after a whole discussion of רוב. rov.
We can make an assumption that most people who are going to
have the חוצפה chutzpah to take up a knife and slaughter an
animal know what they're doing. And therefore we can assume that he
did it correctly. Now I want to point out an interesting fact
which is we are using here רוב rov to override the חזקה
chazakah that the animal is not כשר. kosher. The animal starts as
טריפה, treifa, is not כשר, kosher, right? And we're using this רוב
rov to assume it was done correctly and to override the חזקה.
chazakah. A little bit different than before when the גמרא Gemara said
that even if you checked the knife and you had an expert
or whatever, it's not כשר kosher until you actually check the actual
cut of the trachea and the esophagus. So it is a little
bit of a question here, what level
of knowledge do you need? How definite do you have to be
to override the pre-existing חזקה chazakah that the animal was not כשר?
kosher? Here we're allowing this רוב rov to satisfy that.
Yes. See because maybe to me this seems like more of a
חידוש chiddush because we had all these exceptions, maybe זכותאי, Zekutai, maybe
he's a עכו"ם, akum, maybe he's a...
you could have said that but then ראה ra'ah would have satisfied
it. ראה ra'ah means that you're observing the process, not that you
know anything more about the person.
No, but what you're saying is if there were a doubt about
the person. as a person, what had the correct personal status would
not have been addressed by ראה ra'ah and the statement was that
ראה ra'ah satisfies the problem.
Well, that's why, even though you don't know his personal status, he
can still say that, you know, ראה ra'ah is sufficient.
No, then you don't need ראה. ra'ah. If you're assuming technically correct
and the point is you don't have to worry about personal status,
then you don't need ראה. ra'ah. The fact that you need ראה
ra'ah shows that we have a concern whether it was technically done
correctly and ראה ra'ah is coming to address it. So obviously the
personal status issue is bracketed. It's not so... either you could tell
me one way or the other way whether you're חושש choshesh for
the personal status issues, but that's not obviously what's going on here.
Here there's some problem that's being solved by ראה. ra'ah. Okay, so...
so the גמרא... Gemara... so right, so that is interesting. The גמרא
Gemara says if it's the case that you don't know, then why
do you need ראה? ra'ah? We should assume רוב מצוין אצל שחיטה
מומחין הן. rov metzuyin etzel shechitah mumchin hen. So... מי לא תניא?
mi lo tanya? Now we're going to discuss this principle that רוב
מצוין rov metzuyin are מומחין. mumchin. We assume if you're doing שחיטה
shechitah you know what you're doing. מי לא תניא, mi lo tanya,
do we not teach in a ברייתא? Baraita? הרי שמצאת תרנגולת שחוטה
בשוק, harei shematzata tarnigoles shechuta bashuk, you happen to find a chicken
slaughtered in the marketplace, okay? I mean, now, presumably it means that
it's... I mean, question is, who owns the chicken, why don't you
ask them? But let's say it's your chicken. Your chicken wandered off
and then you found it in the marketplace slaughtered. או שאמר לשלוחו
צא שחוט, o she'amar lishlucho tze shechot, or you told your messenger,
go and slaughter for me, והלך ומצא שחוטה vehalach umatzah shechuta and
your messenger went to the chicken coop and he found that somebody
had come and slaughtered the chicken already. Okay, pretty similar case. So
the only possible difference is like whether in the first case maybe
even the שחיטה shechitah itself was done against your will. Here you
wanted it slaughtered, but still you don't know who slaughtered it. So
can you assume it was slaughtered correctly? So the ברייתא Baraita says:
חזקתו שחוטה. chezkaso shechuta. You can assume that it was done correctly.
עלמא, almah, so we see, אמרינן amrinan we say, רוב מצוין אצל
שחיטה מומחין הן. rov metzuyin etzel shechitah mumchin hen. We assume that
anybody who's slaughtering, if we don't know otherwise, we assume they know
what they're doing. Michael is also correct. We also assume that they're
not a non-Jew and they're not a כותי Kuti and they're not
a מומר, mumar, and we assume all of those things. So we
make a... we, you know, we take the רוב rov that the
person is the right person doing it correctly and if we don't
know otherwise, that's valid. And again, that's pretty amazing that that overrides
the חזקה chazakah that we said yesterday that the animal starts with
the חזקה chazakah of not being kosher. Yes. To slaughter chicken.
Yes. So maybe we can't go from a chicken to... That is
possible, the גמרא Gemara could have made that distinction, that is a
good point. You're right, you're right, the גמרא Gemara could have made
that point. But since it seems to be going by, you know,
by presumably, I mean I'm reading this in, presumably the logic is,
what would you do slaughtering an animal if you didn't know what
you were doing, then if that's the same type of an argument
to make regardless of what type of an animal you are, but
I mean I understand what you're saying, you're saying, okay, but still
some people are arrogant enough to think they know what they're doing
when they're not, but it's more likely they know what they're doing,
you know, when slaughtering chickens than large animals. Like on... Yes. Right.
And it is a much more common skill. You know, that's a
very good point, right, because it could have just said that this
slaughtering chickens is a very common skill so it's a more reasonable
argument. You make a very good point. Let's see where the גמרא
Gemara continues with this. Okay. So... so the גמרא Gemara says... so
let's first see how the גמרא Gemara responds. לעולם דידע ולא גמיר.
le'olam deyada velo gemir. No, the case is that we know he
doesn't know. So if we know he doesn't know, it's an obvious
point, obviously you have to observe, that's everything we've said before. כגון
דשחט קמן חד סימן שפיר. kegon deshachit kamman chad siman shapir. We
saw that he did one of the סימנים, simanim, the trachea, let's
say, correctly, והלכת vehalachta and you left before he slaughtered the other
one.
Now the physical reality of this is very hard because the point
is that as you slaughter, you're cutting both. It's not like you
slaughter and you get one and then you come back and you
get the other. Now the גמרא Gemara does say that you have
to slaughter, you have to either go back and forth or the
knife has to be long enough to make two cuts, meaning it
has to be double the width of the neck of the animal,
so as you're moving it through, it's making two cuts. So I
don't know, I'm not a שוחט. shochet. But maybe the גמרא Gemara
is assuming that not necessarily it always happens, but at least it's
possible that as it's doing the first length, it's getting one סימן
siman and as it continues it's getting the second סימן. siman. Okay,
so it must... the גמרא Gemara has to assume because remember also
you can't take a break and then do the second one, that's
שהייה. shehiyah. So it's a very absurd case. You saw him do
half of it, you turned your head for a second and he
finished it. Okay, so now your question is, you're afraid that in
the finishing he did something incorrectly because he doesn't know the laws.
So maybe he did something incorrectly. Okay, so כגון דשחט קמן חד
סימן שפיר, kegon deshachit kamman chad siman shapir, he did one סימן
siman and he did it correctly.
מהו דתימא אימא מהאי שפיר האי נמי שפיר? maudteima eima midehai shapir
hach nami shapir? Since he started the process correctly, even though it's
always theoretically possible he made a mistake because he doesn't know the
laws, I should assume the end of the process followed the beginning
of the process and was done correctly? קא משמע לן, kamashma lan,
this teaches us האי אסתרומי אסטרימי ליה אידך שמא שהה שמא דרס.
hai isrumey isrami lei idach shema shasha shema daras. The first thing
maybe by chance he got it right, you know, even a stopped
clock is right twice a day. So... by the second סימן, siman,
maybe he made a mistake, maybe he put pressure, maybe he paused.
So even if he did the first half correctly, if you were
not observing the entire thing, you cannot assume the second half was
correct. Okay, so in the end the גמרא Gemara says, you're right,
it's not such a big חידוש, chiddush, it's the principle we said
before. But again, what we're really doing is we're underscoring that even
though a person has experience and even if you see the beginning
of the process correct, if you do not, if we know that
you do not know the laws, we cannot trust you even for
the end of the process; we always have to be concerned that
you might make a mistake at the end. Okay, now again I
just want to point out that, you know, the question of when
you use רוב rov is very questionable here because look at the
difference. If I said this guy has שחט shechted a hundred times
correctly and he did the beginning of this process correct—ah, but since
he doesn't know the laws, maybe this time he ended it incorrectly—well,
what's the chances? Probably the chances are pretty slim. I mean, what,
five percent likelihood or less? Okay,
so right that—nope, sorry, if you don't know for sure and he
doesn't know the laws, no good. On the other hand, a סתם
stam found an animal שחט, shechted, I could say, oh, majority of
people who שחט shecht know what they're doing, right? So when do
I rely on majority, when do I not, is a little, is
a little bit strange. And part of it also seems to be
that the difference here is, is that we're trying to also set
requirements and criteria, meaning we're trying to say, look, you know, if
we are involved in the process, you know, we are trying to
say we demand that somebody pass a test essentially before he can
be a שוחט. shochet. If he failed that test, you know, we're
going to exclude him from being a שוחט shochet because he might
get it wrong. But the focus I think more is like imagine,
you know, you're in the, you know, what do you call it,
you're in the regulatory agency of שחיטה, shechita, right? So you say
there's a test you have to pass. If you fail the test,
even if you know you've done a lot of שחיטות shechitos correctly,
we're not going to let you do it. So that's like, you
know, that seems to be, or the other case where for example
even after you שחט shechted you have to check the cut, that
was because you could check the cut, that's different than a case
here when you סתם stam found an animal שחט shechted and you
just don't know. So you don't know the person failed, you don't
know any fact, right? So in that case you rely on רוב.
rov. But I just want to point out that it's, there is
a big difference, right? Relying on רוב—meaning rov not a difference, it
seems to be an inconsistency. Sometimes we rely on רוב rov even
if you know סתם stam an animal שחט shechted and we have
no knowledge who did it, we're willing to rely on רוב. rov.
On the other hand, you know, we, if, if you don't check
the trachea and the esophagus, even if everything was, was done correctly,
no good. And if a guy did it a million times and
you saw the beginning of the process, if he doesn't pass the
test, also no good. So it is a little interesting when we
do rely on רוב rov when we don't.
It's like a penalty for not checking.
Well, that's what I was getting to, meaning the problem of those
other two cases are not just that there isn't a רוב, rov,
the problem of those other two cases is we're trying to set
standards. So we set a standard, you have to check. We set
a standard, you have to pass a test. When you're not doing
those standards, right, we're not going to allow it even if technically
based on laws of רוב rov we should allow it. Whereas in
the other case you don't know who did it, that's not an
issue of setting standards. So I think that that's exactly the point.
Okay, but now we've introduced this concept of רוב מצויין אצל שחיטה
מומחין. rov metzuyin etzel shechita mumchin. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so בעי מיניה רב דימי בר יוסף מרב נחמן. bei minei
Rav Dimi bar Yosef me-Rav Nachman. So רב דימי בר יוסף Rav
Dimi bar Yosef asked from רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: האומר לשלוחו צא
ושחוט והלך ומצא שחוט מהו? ha-omer lishlucho tze u-shchot ve-halach u-matza shachut
mahu? Okay, so you tell your שליח
shaliach go and שחט, shecht, and the שליח shaliach goes,
you know, and the—and the—and then you go, not the שליח shaliach
goes. The previous case was—was the שליח shaliach went. You go, you
tell your שליח, shaliach, go, go שחט shecht me a chicken. Okay?
And you're waiting an hour, he hasn't come back. You go to
your chicken coop and you see the chicken is שחט. shechted. So
what's the story? Do I assume he did it, or do I
assume some random person did it? So he says, no, אמר ליה
חזקתו שחוט. amar lei chazakato shachut. You can assume the שליח shaliach
did what you said and that it was שחט shechted correctly. Okay,
here's another question: האומר לשלוחו צא ותרום והלך ומצא תרום. ha-omer lishlucho
tze u-trom ve-halach u-matza tarum. You tell your שליח, shaliach, go and
take תרומה terumah from me from my grain. והלך ומצא תרום, ve-halach
u-matza tarum, and you went and you found תרומה terumah was taken,
meaning you found a separate little pile of grain, maybe in a
box labeled תרומה, terumah, whatever. So you found the תרומה terumah was
taken. Can you assume your שליח shaliach did it or maybe some
random person? So the answer is מאי? mai? So אמר ליה אין
חזקתו תרום. amar lei ein chazakato tarum. You cannot assume it was
done correctly. So it's very bizarre. So he says, ממה נפשך, mamma
nafshach, make up your mind. אי חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו—this ei chazaka
shaliach oseh shelichuto is a great question that comes a lot of
places in the גמרא—do Gemara we say that there is a חזקה?
chazaka? Notice here by the way that חזקה chazaka is being used
different than before. This is the חזקה chazaka that דב וינשטוק Dov
Weinstock was referencing yesterday. This is not the חזקה chazaka of status
quo; this is the חזקה chazaka of a presumption we make about
how human beings act. Okay, so the חזקה chazaka is people that
are sent on jobs do their job. If I tell you to
go do something for me—I don't know if you would ask parents
and kids, you know, when they tell their kid, clean your room,
okay—maybe that's why I stopped. It only works for an adult, but
if you tell somebody go do something for me and they say
yes, can we assume they've done it or not? Is it חזקה
שליח עושה שליחותו Chazakah shliach oseh shlichuso or אין חזקה שליח עושה
שליחותו? ein chazakah shliach oseh shlichuso? Which doesn't mean they definitely don't
do it, it just means that you cannot assume that they have
done it. So that's his question. Do we say חזקה שליח עושה
שליחותו? chazakah shliach oseh shlichuso? We have a presumption that the messenger
does what they have been sent to do. If that's true, אפילו
תרומה נמי, afillu trumah nami, so if you tell your messenger go
take תרומה trumah and you found that the תרומה trumah was taken,
you can assume it was your messenger who did it and it's
okay. ואי אין חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו, ve'i ein chazakah shliach oseh
shlichuso, if we cannot assume people do what they have been sent
to do, אפילו שחיטה נמי לא? afillu shechitah nami lo? How come
when you say go שחט shecht and you found that your animal
is שחט-ed, shecht you can eat it? What is the difference if
you don't can't assume your messenger did what you said and some
random person did it, so why can you eat from the שחיטה
shechitah and not from the case where the תרומה trumah was taken?
So there's an obvious answer based on what we said before and
let's take a look. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back
to him, לכי תיכול אלא כור דמלחא, lichi tichol ala kor demilcha,
which is a phrase that is an idiomatic expression when somebody asks
a question which presumably you sort of said, you know, you need
to be thinking about this more. It says, when you weigh out
for me a measure of salt, mean it's like you're asking me
this question, why don't you why don't you stop and think about
it for a while? After you weigh out for me a measure
of salt or do me a favor, do this little favor for
me and then I'll give you an answer. It's some idiomatic expression
which both means
like, either do me a favor and I'll give you an answer,
not literally, or I think it also means it's something you should
have thought about more before asking the question. And so there's an
give me a break, well maybe. And here's the obvious answer. What's
the answer? לעולם אין חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו, leolam ein chazakah shliach
oseh shlichuso,
we do not assume a messenger has done what you've sent them
to do. Yes, we cannot make that assumption. Might depend on דאורייתא
d'oraysa דרבנן d'rabanan whatever, but let's anyway assume that it's possible we
do not assume a messenger does what you send them to do.
I mean if they come back and report they've done it, fine,
but you can't just assume they've done it. So therefore you cannot
assume the תרומה trumah was was done by your messenger, a random
person did it. So why can you eat from
the שחיטה? shechitah? ושחיטה, v'shechitah, because here's the reason, by the case
of שחיטה, shechitah, אי נמי דילמא איניש אחרינא שמע ואזל ועבד, ei
nami dilma inish achrina shama v'azal v'avad, even if it wasn't your
guy who did it, somebody heard you tell your messenger to go
do it and somebody else said, "Oh, I'll do the guy a
favor, I love doing שחיטה," shechitah, and ran ahead and did it
himself.
אי נמי, ei nami,
even even if somebody else did it, רוב מצוין אצל שחיטה מומחין
הן. rov metzuyin etzel shechitah mumchin hein.
As we've said before, it doesn't need to be your messenger. Any
we assume anybody who's doing it knows what they're doing whether they
are or not your messenger. So forget that you told your messenger
to do it. It just goes to the basic case. You found
your animal שחט-ed, shecht you can assume even though the person didn't
have a right to do it, you can assume they know what
they're doing and it was שחט-ed shecht correctly. How is that different
from תרומה? trumah? But by תרומה, trumah, דילמא איניש אחרינא שמע ואזל
ועבד, dilma inish achrina shama v'azal v'avad,
we're concerned that it wasn't your messenger, we're concerned some random person
heard you telling your messenger and said, "Oh, I'll do the guy
a favor," and he went and did it himself. And that's a
problem. Not that he doesn't know what he's doing, but the problem
is הוי ליה תורם שלא מדעת. havei lei torem shelo mida'at. He's
taking תרומה trumah without the knowledge and without the authority given by
the owner. והתורם שלא מדעת אין תרומתו תרומה. vehatorem shelo mida'at ein
trumaso trumah.
Somebody takes תרומה trumah without the knowledge of the owner, it is
not legitimate. ההלכה ha-halachah by תרומה trumah is that the owner has
to be the one to take תרומה trumah or he has to
empower somebody, make a שליח, shliach, transfer the authority for somebody to
do it for him. But if a random person did it, even
though the owner wants the תרומה trumah taken, if he has not
specifically given over that authority to the other person, the other person
is a random person who does it, even though it's the desire
of the owner, it's not a good תרומה. trumah. תרומה's trumah only
by the owner or by somebody empowered by the owner. Okay, so
therefore the basic point is we cannot assume the שליח shliach did
it. We have to be concerned a random person did it. By
שחיטה shechitah that's okay. שחיטה shechitah although I don't have a right
to touch your property if you haven't given me that right, but
okay, that's a separate issue. As far as the שחיטה, shechitah, the
שחיטה shechitah is legitimate. And we assume that any random person who
does שחיטה, shechitah, a person wouldn't have the חוצפה chutzpah to do
שחיטה shechitah unless they knew what they were doing. רוב מצוין אצל
שחיטה מומחין. rov metzuyin etzel shechitah mumchin. By תרומה, trumah, if it
was not the messenger, if it was not the person I empowered,
then even if it was technically done correctly, it's invalid because תרומה
trumah done not by the owner and not by his agent is
invalid. Michael? So just interesting.
So can I empower anyone I want to do תרומה, trumah, meaning
I just
Well, he has to be ראוי לשליחות, ra'uy lishlichus, so yes.
No no, meaning like I don't designate anyone in particular but I
say anyone has the authority, then
כל השומע קולי, kol hashomeia koli, yeah, you can do that.
Okay, fine. The other thing was, you know, let's say I have
one Jewish slave and ten non-Jewish slaves. חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו chazakah
shliach oseh shlichuso and then I should go after the רוב rov
and that means presumably my non-Jewish slave שחט-ed shecht it, in which
case it's no good.
No, how do you know it was a slave? Maybe it was
somebody else. Maybe it was a random person.
I mean I'm in my house and I'm saying to, you know,
whoever it is, you, "Please שחט shecht this for me."
So So you're going back to your question about forget technical knowledge,
what about the personal status? First okay, so first of all I
want to talk slaves because slaves are would be כשר kosher for
שחיטה. shechita. You were talking about non-Jews, okay? You're in a town
where the, you're the one Jewish family in a town that all
non-Jews, okay, and you go and you find your animal is שחט
shechted and you know you're the only person in the town. Nobody
else is in your family, you're the one Jew in the town
and you find your animal שחט. shechted. So that's a very good
point. So in those types of circumstances we would have to say
that even if they... that you know that that would create a
different type of a רוב. rov. You're right. I mean I think
that that this רוב rov is... the other question to ask is
let's say we know that in this town people are highly irresponsible,
right? Let's say this town is a people that are practicing שחיטה
shechita and are you know randomly we know randomly attacking people's animals
like the people that used to dig up graves to do you
know to learn anatomy. So people... and let's say we know that
they're not מומחין mumchin and so in those types of situations I
think things would change, yeah.
And in terms of חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto
or not. I mean I think it would make a difference let's
say you ask your father to do it.
Ah so that's a good question. First the question about do we
rule חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto or not might
depend on דאורייתא de'oraisa or דרבנן. de'rabbanan. And the other question which
is dealt with in a תשובה tshuva of רב משה Rav Moshe
and other תשובות tshuvos is you know does it depend on the
person. If I basically let's say I don't know I'm giving a
השגחה hashgacha to a to a place and I ask and I'm
telling you Michael who I implicitly trust, I would trust you with
my life Michael, and I'm telling you right and I'm telling you
go ahead and take care of A B and C and whatever.
Do I say אין חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו? ein hazaka shaliach oseh
shelichuto? If I personally know that you are always super careful about
those things and do them you know with the with the greatest
care, so that's an issue that the פוסקים poskim talk about and
about the possibility that right that under circumstances might might allow for
for you know for differences here. So yes that is a very
good question. These rules רוב מצויין מומחין, rov metzuyin mumchin, רוב, rov,
חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto etc. can they change
when you know the circumstances to be otherwise? Okay so those are
very good questions and are discussed and sometimes the answer is yes.
There is another question down here. חנן? Hanan? No.
I guess it's the difference between the תרומה terumah case and the
שחיטה shechita case as one is a מצוה mitzvah and one is
not.
Well
that is a good point. You mean why I might assume somebody
else did it?
But also why do you have to...
Oh why you need to be empowered? No oh I see. No
that's a good question. It more has to do with the fact
I would not say that, I would say that oh you're right
I never said why the logic of the difference. I would more
say yes מצוה mitzvah but not just generically מצוה mitzvah but the
focus of the מצוה. mitzvah. The idea of תרומה terumah is you
got this grain you are supposed to you know give from your
grain. So it's not just a מצוה. mitzvah. I mean we make
a ברכה bracha before שחיטה shechita אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על השחיטה.
asher kidshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu al hashechita. Okay so but the point is
is that there it's not like you are supposed to slaughter your
animals right? It's more generic. If you want to eat meat the
meat has to be slaughtered. Where here it's you're supposed to give
from your grain to the כהן. kohen. It's very much about your
personal relationship. So the מצוה mitzvah shapes it but it's not just
the fact that it's a מצוה. mitzvah. It's a מצוה mitzvah about
you and your relationship to your grain. So it's about the it's
about the ownership. Okay Seth did you have a question?
So whether you can use a שליח shaliach for that... but the
word שליח shaliach especially סתמו stamo yes דווקא davka assumes not in
the case where he needs to be a שליח shaliach in תרומה.
terumah.
In שחיטה shechita
he's not your שליח.
shaliach. Right.
Meaning whether שליח shaliach means a guy doing a favor for me
or שליח shaliach means the formal laws of agency. It's absolutely correct
by תרומה terumah if it's used loosely not in a halachicly meaningful
way I do not have to make him my שליח. shaliach. I
just have to ask him and then אין חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו
ein
hazaka shaliach
oseh shelichuto you can't assume. Right. But תרומה terumah no but by
תרומה terumah it will be good if he does if he does
it if he comes back and tells me he's done it but
right there שליח shaliach means the technical meaning of the word שליח.
shaliach. Absolutely correct. Okay look the very important relevance of this if
you look to the side you see where it was originally quoted
חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto by the asterisk גיטין
סד Gittin samech daled
right? The big question is I send my שליח shaliach to give
a גט get to my wife okay and she lives you know
halfway around the world or even if she lives in the next
town can I assume he's done it or do I have to
hear back and know for sure that he's done it? Right? Or
maybe for me it doesn't make such a difference but let's say
she sends a שליח shaliach to receive her גט. get. Can she
assume that the גט get has been received or does she have
to know that it's... so there you know these are the types
of questions about חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. hazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto. Obviously
when they report back you know they've done it. But can you
make assumptions without them you know without them reporting back? That's where
those questions lie. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Where are we?
Okay
ורוב מצויין... verov metzuyin... לימא leima let us say says the גמרא
Gemara רוב מצויין אצל שחיטה מומחין הן. rov metzuyin etzel shechita mumchin
hen. This question of whether if the majority of people who are
going to do a שחיטה shechita we can assume they know what
they're doing. תנאי היא tannai hi it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim.
How do you why would we say that? דתניא detanya we taught
in a ברייתא braita הרי שאבדו לו גדייו ותרנגוליו. harei she-avdu lo
gedayav vetarnigolav.
Your your kid goats or your chickens ran away. Got lost. והלך
ומצאן שחוטים. vehalach u'matzan shechutim.
And then you found them, unfortunately you found them and they were
שחט. shechted. So I don't know what happened, somebody found them, thought
they were going to have some fun, thought they were his, שחט
shechted it, realized they weren't his, so left them. Okay. Anyway, רבי
יהודה אוסר, Rabbi Yehuda oser, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says they're forbidden,
you can't assume that they were שחט shechted correctly. ורבי חנינא בנו
של רבי יוסי הגלילי מתיר v'Rabbi Chanina beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili
matir and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says they were they are okay.
So here it seems like exactly that question. You don't know who
שחט shechted it. Can you assume correct or not correct? Again, Rivka's
point is legitimate that we're not talking about בהמה גסה, behema gassa,
we're talking about chickens and goats, which maybe it's more reasonable to
assume it was correct. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara does
with it, or the ברייתא Baraisa תוספתא Tosefta does with it. Yes?
So we're not talking about like you actually looked and you saw
that the trachea and the esophagus was severed, what if it was
cut in like 15 different pieces?
Right, correct. And that's also presumed, that's an important point. Again, all
the גמרות Gemaros we've been seeing, right? About let's say, you know,
about ignore the earlier discussion about checking the actual cut itself, right?
Is רוב מצויים אצל שחיטה מומחין הן, rov metzuyim etzel shechita mumchin
hein, is that because it's bolstered by the fact that you've inspected
the בית השחיטה beis hashechita and you've seen that they were שחט
shechted correctly? If so, the argument makes a lot more sense. But
the גמרא Gemara isn't saying that, right? So that's like an that's
I think an open question. Like we also said what was it
two days ago a whole issue about oh, yet your knife got
a nick, when did it get a nick? Well, why don't you
also look at the בית השחיטה? beis hashechita? That should be relevant
evidence for when it got the nick. So it's very interesting that
these גמרות Gemaros ignore the whole statement that was said earlier because
it really was an independent statement and is not necessarily integrated into
these discussions that you have to check the you know afterwards. So
it's unclear whether that checking will matter one way or the other.
These סוגיות sugyos are ignoring it.
But this is also שחוטים shechutim as opposed to טבוחים tevuchim where
it really would not make a difference. Meaning like שחוטים? shechutim? No,
no, no. But like they were chopped up.
Oh, meaning you could not even observe. No, I would assume forget
checking the trachea and the esophagus. I would assume that if you
had no visual evidence that it looked like a שחיטה shechita then
you could not say רוב מצויים אצל שחיטה. rov metzuyim etzel shechita.
Because maybe you know a non-Jew got it and slaughtered it that
way. No, רוב מצויים אצל שחיטה rov metzuyim etzel shechita means you
start by the fact that what you are observing you can observe
that an act of שחיטה shechita was done. And then the question
was just was it done correctly? And did the person know what
he was doing?
It's not like you found them with a little tag that says...
Right, no no. That no, no, no.
Okay. So there's a debate whether it's okay. And then we'll see
רבי. Rebbi. אמר רבי, amar Rebbi, רבי Rebbi says, נראין דברי רבי
יהודה, nirin divrei Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says they're no
good, that makes sense שמצאן באשפה, shematzan b'ashpa, you found them in
the dung heap, right? Or in the garbage dump. Because what are
they doing in the garbage dump unless the guy שחט shechted it
and made a mistake so he's throwing it out? Of course, you
know, I don't know why he doesn't make it into dog food
or sell to non-Jews, but okay. ודברי רבי חנינא בנו של רבי
יוסי הגלילי v'divrei Rabbi Chanina beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili who says
we assume they are good, שמצאן בבית, shematzan b'bayis, you found them
inside of a house. So therefore your house, somebody else's house. Okay.
So therefore you assume they're okay. All right, which means fundamentally we
say that people we assume they're good unless you have evidence because
they were thrown out that they're not good. So the גמרא Gemara
says, מאי לאו, mai lav, is it not that this is what
they're debating?
בהא קמיפלגי. beha kamifligi. דמר סבר demar savar רבי חנינא בנו של
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Chanina beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili says that
they're always good, I'm meaning we say רוב מצויים אצל שחיטה מומחין
הן, rov metzuyim etzel shechita mumchin hein, that we do assume people
know what they're doing. ומר סבר u'mar savar and the one who
says they're no good, לא אמרינן רוב מצויים אצל שחיטה מומחין הן.
lo amrinan rov metzuyim etzel shechita mumchin hein. We don't assume that
if somebody שחט shechted it he knew what he was doing. And
רבי Rebbi obviously says that we fundamentally do unless there's evidence that
it was a נבלה. neveila. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, לא, lo, that's not necessarily the debate. דכולי
עלמא dekulei alma I can argue that everybody, even רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who is מחמיר machmir says, רוב מצויים אצל שחיטה מומחין הן,
rov metzuyim etzel shechita mumchin hein, that they all we always assume
people know what they're doing. So therefore why does רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda say it's no good? Because it depends on the circumstances. ובבית
u'v'bayis if it was found in a house, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי
דשרי. dekulei alma lo peligi deshari. Everybody would agree that it's okay.
Even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say we assume if somebody שחט,
shechted, he knew what he was doing. באשפה b'ashpa if you found
them in a dung heap שבשוק she'bashuk it was a public dung
heap, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסור. dekulei alma lo peligi d'assur. Everybody
would agree nobody you don't throw it out in a public dung
heap unless you know it's worthless and unless you unless you didn't
do it correctly. כי פליגי ki peligi what was the whole debate
about? באשפה שבבית, b'ashpa shebabayis, your private garbage dump. Now again, I
understand that if it's if it's public you're totally ridding yourself of
it, so obviously it's worthless. But it still doesn't exactly answer if
it was שחט shechted well why did you put it in your
in even in your private garbage dump? So I don't exactly understand
unless the point is well maybe it happened to fall there, you
left it in the house and your wife came along and she
didn't know so she just moved it to the garbage. Who knows?
Okay, it's a little strange, but we're assuming that there is some
ambiguity when it's in your private garbage what its status is. Okay
and that's the debate.
מר סבר mar savar אדם עשוי להטיל נבלתו באשפה שבבית, adam assui
lehatil neveilato b'ashpa shebabayis, one רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says it's
forbidden says a person will normally throw out a נבלה, neveila, your
incorrectly שחט shechted animal, into your private garbage dump. ומר סבר u'mar
savar and the other holds אין אדם עשוי להטיל נבלתו באשפה שבבית.
ein adam assui lehatil neveilato b'ashpa shebabayis. No, you would not... Not
put it in your private one because it's going to get smelly
and attract vermin and flies and who knows what? So if you're
really leaving it because you're throwing it out, you would take it
to the public garbage stop. If it's in your house one, somehow
it got moved there incorrectly, but if it really were an עבלה
aveila you would not leave it in your home garbage, it's too
big of a health and hygiene hazard. So the whole debate is,
we assume you know, we assume if in normal case of שחיטה
shechita the person knew what he was doing, if you don't know
otherwise, and the question is how do we interpret the fact that
it's in your private garbage dump? Do you your private do we
assume that that tells us that this was done incorrectly? Okay, so
now we're going to see if that explanation can really hold in
the ברייתא. braita. אמר מר, Amar mar, so we're going to re-quote
the ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי, Amar Rebbi, says Rebbi, נראין דברי רבי
יהודה שמצאן באשפה. Nirin divrei Rebbi Yehuda shemetza'an beashpah. So it says
Rebbi Yehuda seems correct when they're in the dump. So מאי אשפה,
mai ashpah, which meaning if Rebbi Yehuda seems correct in that case,
that means Rebbi Yehuda has to forbid more cases, but we're only
ceding Rebbi Yehuda's position, you know, agreeing to it in the case
of the dump. So מאי אשפה, mai ashpah, which dump is Rebbi
agreeing to? אילימא אשפה שבשוק, Ileima ashpah shebashuk, the public garbage dump,
הא מדכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסר, ha midekuli alma lo pligi deasar,
so then even everybody agrees that that's forbidden, you don't rule like
Rebbi Yehuda if that's if you just said there it's agreed that
that's not good. אלא לאו, Ela lav, so what are we talking
about? פשיטא באשפה שבבית, Pshita beashpah shebebayit, you mean the your your
a home garbage, your private garbage. Okay, so Rebbi is saying I
rule like Rebbi Yehuda in the case of the garbage, even your
home garbage. All right, let's look at the end of this. אימא
סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the end of Rebbi's statement. ודברי
רבי חנינא בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי שמצאן בבית. Vedivrei Rebbi Chanina
beno shel Rebbi Yose HaGelili shemetza'an bebayit. We rule like that it's
that it's okay when the animal was found in the house. מאי
בית, Mai bayit, what do you mean in the house? אילימא בית
ממש, Ileima bayit mamash, if you literally mean in the house, הא
מר דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי, ha mar dekuli alma lo pligi
deshari, you said everybody agrees that's okay, even Rebbi Yehuda says it's
okay, so you don't have to rule like the other opinion if
everybody agrees it's okay. So אלא פשיטא, ela pshita, what is left
to what might you mean, where is there an area of debate?
באשפה שבבית, Beashpah shebebayit, the house doesn't mean the house in the
normal place of the house, it means in the garbage dump of
the house. So how can first you rule strictly in the garbage
dump of the house and then leniently? Meaning, another way to re-phrase
this is, Rebbi, when Rebbi says we're going to rule like one
opinion by the garbage dump and the other opinion by the house,
it sounds like the debate covers all of those cases. As opposed
to what we're trying to do, which is to limit the debate
to the very narrow case of a private garbage dump. So it
doesn't sound like that then Rebbi would not have to have ruled
one way in one case and one way in the other case.
So קשיא דרבי אדרבי, Kashya deRebbi aRebbi, the way you're reading it
now Rebbi contradicts himself. In one case he rules the private garbage
dump is okay and in the other case he rules the private
garbage dump is not okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, all right,
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's how you have to read Rebbi. Not
like he is splitting his vote, but that Rebbi is actually interpreting
and limiting what is the debate itself. So here's what Rebbi means.
נראין דברי רבי יהודה לרבי חנינא בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי, Nirin
divrei Rebbi Yehuda leRebbi Chanina beno shel Rebbi Yose HaGelili, when he
says we rule like Rebbi Yehuda by a garbage dump, it doesn't
mean literally we rule like Rebbi Yehuda by garbage dump, it really
means nobody debates the garbage dump. Rebbi Yehuda's position that it's not
good even רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rebbi Yose bar Chanina would admit
to in a case of a garbage dump. So his position that
it's not good is would would you know is would be conceded
by רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose HaGelili באשפה שבשוק, beashpah shebashuk, in
a public garbage dump. שעד רבי חנינא בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי
לא נחלק עליו אלא באשפה שבבית, She'ad Rebbi Chanina beno shel Rebbi
Yose HaGelili lo nechelak alav ela beashpah shebebayit, because even he was
not debating the public garbage dump, he was only debating the private
one. אבל באשפה שבשוק מודה ליה, Aval beashpah shebashuk modeh leh, he
would agree to the case of the public. ונראין וכולי, Venirin vechulu,
the גמרא Gemara doesn't finish ending the statement, but the point is
the end of Rebbi's statement would be, and when Rebbi says it
is good, even Rebbi Yehuda would admit to that in the case
of the house. So meaning when Rebbi when Rebbi is saying we're
going to rule like this one in this case and this one
in this case, so which seems to say that their debate spans
all of the cases, the גמרא Gemara is re-framing it. No, I
don't mean we're going to rule like him in this case. I
mean that this case, this extreme, everybody agrees is not good, the
public garbage dump. The other extreme, the house, not we rule that
it's okay. The other extreme, the house, everybody agrees it is good.
So the only debate is in the narrow middle case about the
private garbage dump and that's where they debate.
So is that what we were saying before?
No, before we were saying they they debated the span, but we
ruled like one extreme like one person and the other extreme the
other person. Now we're trying to say they don't debate the span,
they only debate the narrow middle case, and what Rebbi is saying
is, and Rebbi is making that statement, we rule not we rule
like him because he held position it was debated there. It means
everybody agrees in that extreme.
Everybody agrees in the other extreme.
Yes, but we're reading רב נחמן Rav Nachman into Rebbi. Rebbi seems
to say not that way. We're not saying something different, we're just
reconciling what Rebbi seems to be saying. Okay, fine. Anyway, so the
way we end here is that we do say רוב מצויין אצל
שחיטה מומחין הן. Rov metzuyin etzel shechita mumchin hen. So again, I
want to remind you, what are the requirements? The requirements are before
we let somebody do שחיטה, shechita, we have to. Chapter number one,
know that they passed the test. You have to know that they
know what they're doing. It was a little bit unresolved whether we
have to actually have seen them have had experience, supervised experience, which
of course all of us take for granted that you would require,
but it was a little less clear in the גמרא, Gemara, where
the גמרא Gemara maybe book knowledge was sufficient to let a guy
start, but, and I'm trying to remember, I think we actually even
פוסקין pasken at least in theory that way, that a person does
not have to actually have demonstrated experience, which is a little shocking,
but okay, that was debated. But if they actually have failed the
test,
then even if they have had tons of experience, if they've failed
the test, we cannot eat from their שחיטה, shechita, because maybe this
time they made a mistake. And if we don't know whether they
know or not, and we just found an animal shechted, or we
saw a guy shecht and then he went away, and we don't
know who was that masked man who did all this שחיטה, shechita,
right? So we don't know, then we use this principle רוב מצויים
אצל שחיטה מומחין הן. rov metzuyim etzel shechita mumchin hen. We assume
that if somebody was doing it, that they did know the laws,
they did know what they were doing. And again I want to
point out that this is quite interesting. The animal starts with a
חזקת איסור chezkat issur and we have to know that it was
shechted correctly, and here knowing, using this רוב rov suffices for our
criterion of knowing that it was done correctly. Now maybe it's bolstered
by the fact that we inspected the סימנים, simanim, but the גמרא
Gemara doesn't discuss that. So it's a little bit interesting that this
רוב rov suffices to override the previous חזקה chazaka that it was
not good. But other types of things we did not go by
רוב, rov, like you know we said that even if everything was
perfect, if you didn't check the סימנים simanim they're no good. So
the point I was trying to make about this, which חנן Chanan
said as well, is that maybe it's not so much do we
rely on רוב rov or not. In principle we do rely on
רוב, rov, but if we're trying to set standards, then if you
have violated those standards we're not going to let you do it.
So if the standard is you have to pass the test before
you can be a שוחט shochet and you failed the test, then
you know, we're not going to allow somebody to eat from that
שחיטה shechita even if you have had years of experience. If our
standard is that you have to check the סימנים simanim and you
don't check the סימנים, simanim, we're not going to let you eat
from it even if everything else was done correctly. So I think
it's interesting to think about that, when we are using the רוב
rov and when we're not using the רוב. rov. Okay, so now
we get back to, so we had, so this is actually, we've
just now covered about 11 דף daf from the beginning of the
משנה, Mishnah, time really flies. The beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, as
you'll remember, talked about the people that were good or not, חרש
שוטה וקטן הכל שוחטין cheresh shotah ve'katan hakol shochtin led to a
whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara about a מומר, mumar, about you
know about a כותי kuti and so on, and then we had
this whole, and then you know knowledge, experience, all the question about
the personal qualifications, with a very important digression into the areas of
רוב rov and חזקה. chazaka. Now we're sort of coming full circle
and we're getting back to the משנה, Mishnah, who can and cannot,
and the key people the משנה Mishnah discusses is the חרש שוטה
וקטן. cheresh shotah ve'katan. They cannot because they'll make mistakes, even if
they know what they're, even if they pass a million tests, we
assume they'll make
mistakes, unless they are being directly observed. So let's take a look.
חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן, chutz micheresh shotah ve'katan, anybody can shecht with
the exception of the חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shotah ve'katan, שמא יקלקלו
שחיטתן, shema yekalkelu shechitatan, lest they mess it up, mess up their
שחיטה. shechita. Unless they are directly observed and you see they have
not. So the גמרא Gemara says: שמא קלקלו לא תני, shema kilkelu
lo tana, we did not say lest they actually did mess it
up in the past, אלא שמא יקלקלו, ella shema yekalkelu, lest they
will mess it up in the future. So what does that tell
you? אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava says: זאת אומרת אין
מוסרין להם חולין לכתחילה, zot omeret en mosrin lahem chullin lechatchila, we
do not, you are not allowed to give them animals to shecht
לכתחילה. lechatchila. Now what does that mean? If you're not going to
observe it of course you're not allowed because it says if they
shechted without being observed it's not good. So רש"י Rashi says this
means even if you're planning on observing them, okay, even if you're
planning on observing them we are so concerned that they'll mess it
up, you know, sometimes, first of all even if you observe them
you can observe them messing it up. So fine, so fine, you're
not going to eat a טרף, treif, a נבילה, neveila, but you're
going to waste a nice a good cow. Okay, so we do
not want you to give it to them even if you're planning
on observing, we're so concerned that they'll mess it up in the
future. If you want to look at רש"י, Rashi, he said about
ten lines down in the narrow lines, beginning of the lines: זאת
אומרת אין מוסרין להם חולין, zot omeret en mosrin lahem chullin, כלומר
אפילו חולין לכתחילה ואפילו אחרים עומדין על גבן. klomar afilu chullin lechatchila
ve'afilu acherim omdin al gaban. Why? Because they're just so likely to
mess it up, it's being irresponsible to do such a thing. Okay,
so that's, which is interesting even though there would not really be
a halachic consequence, I mean the halachic consequence I guess would be
בל תשחית, bal tashchit, but that's the way רש"י Rashi reads this
statement. Okay. And now we're going to get to the issue of
direct observation
for when he's a גדול gadol then?
Right, exactly. Exactly. That would be the, the נפקא מינה nafa mina
of that, right? If you wanted to start your קטנים ktanim off
on a whole training thing where you know, now again the question
that you could ask similar to your other questions is let's say
you know your child is super coordinated and, you know, right, so
would this prohibition apply? If you knew in your particular case it
was different.
Right, shechting on non-kosher animals?
Shechting on, oh, that's interesting question. Maybe, right? Maybe, I don't see,
even
a
בל תשחית... bal tashchit...
No so he says, no he says רש"י *Rashi*'s correct you don't
do it לכתחילה *lechatchila* even with observing but he just says that
that's obvious. So he says
oh so רבנו תם *Rabbenu Tam* says even if you're planning on
selling it to non-Jews or using for dog food
why because other people will make a mistake. Once you have once
you see a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan *cheresh shoteh vekoton*
doing it even if you're not going to even if you're planning
on using it for dog food or whatever, people, it'll lead people
to thinking you can rely on the שחיטה shchita *shechita* of a
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan *cheresh shoteh vekoton*. So רבנו תם
*Rabbenu Tam* leads it even in a more extreme case what, oh
maybe if it's only not your case of non-kosher animals that would
be different. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues בכולן ששחטו
ואחרים רואים אותן *bekulan sheshachtu veacherim roim osan* but if they were
under direct observation שחיטתן כשרה *shechitason kesheira* then at least בדיעבד bedi'avad
*bedieved* it's okay. מאן תנא *man tanna*? Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has a question right because now you're having a חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh ve-katan *cheresh shoteh vekoton* doing it so technically it's correct.
But the question we need to ask is חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh ve-katan *cheresh shoteh vekoton* are normally not considered to be adult
well not just adults what's the word like בר דעת da'at. *bar
daas* is the technical what competent right in normal halachic matters and
doesn't just mean the technical
meaning like for religious for example okay a
קטן katan, *koton* can't count to a מנין *minyan* or can't write
a ספר תורה *Sefer Torah* or whatever it might be right because
these are things which basically to be to execute to be considered
fit ritually fit not just able to technically do it correctly you
have to be an adult. Now that's not always the case. Very
often those are issues in which like for example the focus as
Hananya was saying earlier the focus is a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*. So
if you're a minor or חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan *cheresh
shoteh vekoton* then you cannot execute a מצוה mitzvah? *mitzvah* but sometimes
if it's just about the physical performance of an act it doesn't
matter that you're a minor. But one thing in theory that the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* could have asked which it doesn't is how could
a קטן katan *koton* do it we need an adult. Now normally
though that's because the תורה *Torah* says somewhere איש *ish*, איש איש
*ish ish* if a person a man so איש להוציא את הקטן
*ish lehotzi es hakoton* excludes a minor for example by יבום *yibbum*
which is something you would certainly think maybe requires adults because it's
affected through an act of sex. Nevertheless there are positions as we
saw before that as long as you're not worried that the person
is going to turn out to be sterile the act of יבום
*yibbum* can even be done even before the קטן *koton* or the
brother or the sister-in-law are adults as long as they're old enough
that it's considered to be halachically an act of sex. So we
don't always assume you need adults. It's usually limited to things where
it's about fulfilling a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* which you might have said
יבום *yibbum* is but יבום *yibbum* also has the reality of effecting
the marriage or things that require sort of like changing status being
empowered to change status like to engage in a type of a
transaction to free a slave to marry a woman to
be married by a man things that are about effecting a change
of
status through so those are things that you require an adult or
that the תורה *Torah* happens to say איש *ish* and we use
that. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interestingly does not assume that שחיטה
shchita. *shechita* is a problem. Number one it never says איש *ish*
by שחיטה shchita, *shechita*. It's by the way the תורה *Torah* never
really talks about a ritual act of שחיטה shchita *shechita* anyway it
just uses a verb it says וזבח *vezovach* which we say means
like the act of שחיטה shchita *shechita* but it never talks about
the technical requirement. It's not a type of it's something that is
affected by being done physically correctly as opposed to if you consider
like an act of a
transaction or getting married or marrying or getting married it's not just
about the physical act it's about effecting a change of status and
requires a בר דעת da'at *bar daas*. This is very much about
the physical act so that's why once the physical act is done
correctly it can even be done by a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh ve-katan *cheresh shoteh vekoton*. But that's first we should acknowledge that
that's a little unusual. Normally we assume that these guys are categorically
excluded. But here we're being told that once it's done technically correctly
because שחיטה shchita, *shechita* is basically about a physical act it's okay.
But now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is actually going to question it
because it says how do we? Maybe there's a criteria in the
act itself that requires a בר דעת da'at *bar daas* not like
you're fundamentally doing an act of changing status but maybe the act
to be considered a legitimate act requires כוונה kavanah. *kavannah* requires that
you intend to do what you are doing
an act of שחיטה shchita, *shechita* like?
Well let's take a look what that means not the מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah* but כוונה kavanah *kavannah*. So let's take a look.
Women included in this grouping as well?
Women are totally לכתחילה *lechatchila*. They're not בדיעבד *bedieved* they're totally לכתחילה
*lechatchila* even for שחיטות קרבנות *shechitos korbanos*. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this.
We can't make a negative כוונה kavanah.
*kavannah*. Alright alright let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says. מאן תנא *man tanna*. So you're telling me חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan is good? Okay, I accept they're not categorically
excluded. I accept this is basically about a physical act, everything I
told you. But you're also implicitly saying that you don't need intent.
You don't need to intend that you're doing an act of שחיטה
shchita? because we are assuming that a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh
ve-katan cannot even have the necessary intent to define what they're doing
as the proper act. So who is the one that says that?
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava says רבי נתן, Rabbi
Natan, he's רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. דתני detani אושעיא זעירא, Oshaiya Zeira,
the younger אושעיא, Oshaiya, דמן חברייא, demin Chavraiya, from חברייא. Chavraiya. So
רש״י Rashi says it means from the ישיבה, yeshiva, תוספות Tosafot says
it was a place called חברייא. Chavraiya. So whatever this younger אושעיא
Oshaiya taught, the following ברייתא. braita. זרק סכין לנועצה בכותל, Zarak sakin
linoatza bakotel,
somebody throws a knife and they're just having fun, they're playing darts.
Okay, they're throwing knives against the wall. Okay, and what happens? לנועצה
בכותל, linoatza bakotel, והלכה ושחטה כדרכה. vehalcha veshachta kedarka.
It happens that there was a cow standing there and it went
right by the cow's neck and it did a good שחיטה. shchita
But you weren't trying to do a שחיטה, shchita, you were just
trying to throw a knife. Okay, is it כשר kosher or not?
רבי נתן מכשיר, Rabbi Natan machshir, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says it's
good, וחכמים פוסלין, vechachamim poslin, and the rabbis say it's no good.
מאן
תני לה אבויה man tani lah avuya taught this ברייתא braita and
he made the following comment: הלכה כרבי נתן, halacha keRabbi Natan, we
rule like רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but והא בעינן מוליך ומביא, veha
be'inan molich umeivi, the act of שחיטה shchita. is going back and
forth, and this was just obviously the knife did not go back
and forth. So it says שהלכו בא כדרכה, shehalchu bah kedarka, that
it went and came back in its normal way. What does this
mean? So it means רש״י Rashi says it means that it bounced
off of the wall and came back, which is pretty amazing that
it did that without שהייה. shehiya. The animal must have been standing
right near the wall or something. The other possibility, and maybe that's
even what the גמרא Gemara means, is right, is that the knife
was very long. And if the knife is the length of twice
the length of the neck of the animal, you don't have to
go back and forth, because one swipe of the knife does the
cutting of going back and forth, because it's twice the length of
the neck of the animal. Which is which is basically, I'm pretty
sure how, you know, שחיטה shchita is done nowadays. It's not with
a back and forth, it's with anyway, that is with it maybe,
I don't know, I'm not sure. But anyway, that could have also
been what the גמרא Gemara, meant, that it was a very long
knife and you didn't need it to go back and forth. Okay,
so regardless, let's talk about this issue of כוונה. kavanah Okay, כוונה
kavanah. is, there are two types of כוונה. kavanah. כוונה kavanah is
what I was saying before without using the technical terms, was there's
one category called דעת. da'at, דעת da'at is in
כוונה. kavanah דעת da'at, is: I am effecting a change of status,
I am selling you my object, I am purchasing an object, I
am making you my wife, I am divorcing you from being my
wife. Yes, there's a physical act that goes with it, right, giving
of a גט, get, giving of a ring, whatever it is. But
fundamentally, it's about, you know, when we say in a lot of
these things, right, you know, we sort of say it's about a
meeting of the minds and the act is more secondary. And there
it's fundamentally about
my being empowered and my changing the status with doing this act.
That's something of דעת, da'at. which we say חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh ve-katan are categorically excluded from. Not because they can't they don't
know that stuff, maybe they do maybe they don't, just הלכתית halachically
we say that you have to be an adult
and of right mind to be able to be empowered to do
that. That's דעת da'at issues. This is not דעת, this is about
a physical act. But even when you deal with physical acts, there's
ideas of כוונה. kavanah, The best place to see this is when
we talk about acts of מצוה. mitzvah. Right, there's a discussion in
the גמרא Gemara whether מצות צריכות כוונה mitzvot tzrichot kavanah or not.
Do you need כוונה kavanah, for מצוה? mitzvah, So that means when
I am doing an act like blowing a שופר shofar or reading
of the שמע Shma or reading of the מגילה, Megilla, do I
have to intend that I am doing this as a מצוה mitzvah,
act or not? Okay, and if you say מצות צריכות כוונה, mitzvot
tzrichot kavanah, I have to say I'm not just reading the מגילה
Megilla or blowing a שופר, shofar, I am doing it as a
מצוה act. That's a higher level of כוונה kavana, you might need
for מצוה. But the גמרא Gemara says, even if you say מצות
mitzvot don't need כוונה, kavana if I don't even realize I'm blowing
a שופר, shofar, let's say I'm trying to clean it out, I'm
blowing through it to clean it out. And as I'm blowing through
it to clean it out, a sound is made. So I wasn't
even trying to do the act of blowing, I was just trying
to clean it out. That the גמרא Gemara says means you can't
define my act as an act of blowing a שופר. shofar. That's
מתעסק. mitasek. מתעסק mitasek means it was totally incidental. Okay, so even
if מצות mitzvot don't need כוונה, kavana. that means you don't have
to intend to do the מצוה, but you have to intend to
do the act of reading מגילה, Megilla, the act of blowing a
שופר, shofar, or else it's completely incidental. That's the גמרא's Gemara concern
here. The גמרא Gemara by the case of throwing the knife against
the wall and it שחטed, shacht meaning I wasn't even doing an
act of שחיטה, shchita I was doing an act of playing darts.
Is it enough that it is physically done correctly? Is that the
only requirement by שחיטה, shchita that it be physically done correctly, or
does it have to be defined as an act of שחיטה? shchita.
That's the question of, because normally we say that if something was
incidental, I can't consider it
to be because we say you have to do a מעשה שחיטה,
ma'aseh shchita, right?
You have to blow שופר shofar on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you
did שחיטה shchita? just like a matter. You know what I mean?
I understand. I understand that but normally we would say, let’s say
by a ברית מילה, bris milah, would you say somebody who had
done a ברית מילה bris milah in a storm as you could
imagine it, right? I mean normally we say for something to count,
the act to be significant, it has to be defined as an
act of שחיטה, shchita. especially I would add the fact that there
are all of these criteria like שהייה, shehiya, דרסה, derasa, whatever, are
to say that there’s a definition, a halachic definition of what constitutes
an act of שחיטה. shchita So as such, the גמרא Gemara what
it’s asking here is an extremely central question: is what defines kosher
שחיטה shchita just the fact that it was physically the correct act,
or is there some halachic definition of it as a מעשה שחיטה
maaseh shchita which is required? And when it occurs incidentally without the
intent to shecht, it’s not—it might have been the same physical act,
but it is not a מעשה שחיטה. maaseh shchita. That is the
question about whether שחיטה shchita requires כוונה, kavana, not to be יוצא
yotzei a מצוה, but the point is, is שחיטה shechita? more than
just the physical act? Does it need to be defined as such?
You need to realize you’re doing an act of שחיטה. Now, what
is troubling about the גמרא, Gemara I will say, is that the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that a חרש cheresh, שוטה shoteh וקטן cannot
provide that. And that is not so clear, and that’s what we’re
going to get to in a minute. Meaning, I understand that a
חרש שוטה וקטן cannot be considered an agent to marry, to divorce,
to sell, to buy, to do those types of things. That makes
sense to me. But to tell me that they cannot, you know,
that every act that they’re doing is considered to be completely, you
know, incidental, that they’re not—we don’t say that they know what their
acts are and that they’re defining their acts, right? And it’s like
they’re just completely doing random things. Maybe in an extreme case of
a שוטה you could say that, but a חרש, a קטן, somebody
you know who is a boy who is twelve and a half
years old, eleven and a half years old, you say what they’re
doing is completely incidental? There’s no even כוונה kavana in what they’re
doing? That is very strange, and there are other things that imply
that a חרש שוטה וקטן do have כוונה. kavana They don’t have
דעת. So this is a strange גמרא in its assumption that חרש
שוטה וקטן don’t have כוונה, kavana. but what’s very important is the
question which we’ll get to later: what defines שחיטה? Is it just
the physical act or does it somehow need to formally be defined
as a מעשה שחיטה? maaseh shchita? גמרא says שחיטה.
This גמרא says that we rule that you don’t require כוונה kavana,
and that’s why חרש שוטה וקטן can do it. But I’m just
saying you could have said a different position: we do require כוונה
kavana and חרש שוטה וקטן can provide the כוונה. kavana Okay, that
the גמרא is not saying. We’ll see more about that in a
bit in a minute. Yes, Daniel.
Same question whether it can be automated, like a machine?
So that’s a good point. It is a very similar question, right?
And when they have for example the making of מצות, matzos, right?
And you need like לשמה lishma by מצות matzos or other types
of things, they actually have questions, they do have questions about can
you have some type of an automated שחיטה factory, etc.? And that
would be a very similar thing. Now, part of the issue there
is what are one of the physical realities that might be—that are
required by שחיטה
might
not be כוונה, kavana? but even in terms of the physical realities
is something called כוח גברא. koach gavra. It has to come through
human agency or through human power, you know, energy. So the question
is that if I push a button and the rest happens by
itself, you know if I open up the dam and the water
starts turning a water wheel and that powers something, is that all
considered like it’s all coming through כוח גברא koach gavra or not?
And those are issues that are discussed. But that’s another aspect here
which is כוח גברא. koach gavra. No, כוונה kavana. means it’s all—because
כוח גברא koach gavra is the physical reality, it comes through human
power. Okay, but the כוונה kavana. is that even with all of
that, do I have to intend that it’s an act of שחיטה
or not to define it as the act? Yes.
I don’t see how this example is relevant since one of the
requirements is to check the knife first. So if you intend to
play darts, you’re not checking the knife.
Well again, you could have a case that you checked the knife
afterwards, בדיעבד that’s okay, or somebody stole—I’m a שוחט shochet and my
friend saw my knives and he was irresponsible and I had checked
the knives and he’d grabbed them and he started playing darts. I
mean you make up some scenario, okay, but you can always check
the knife afterwards and if it’s still good you’re okay. All right,
so let’s begin the next גמרא which gets to this question about
how much we can assume a חרש שוטה וקטן can provide in
different cases. So let’s take a look.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא בעי רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba ba'ei Rabbi Yochanan: קטן יש לו מחשבה או אין לו מחשבה?
Katan yesh lo machshava o ein lo machshava? Does the קטן have
thought or not? Now again, this is not a question about do
minors think about things. It means halachically is their intentions relevant or
not? Which in a way you could read as a possible critique
of the previous סוגיא. sugya. Why are we assuming they don’t have
כוונה? kavana. Maybe they do have כוונה. Maybe their intentions are relevant.
They don’t have דעת but maybe they have מחשבה. machshava. Here it’s
using the phrase מחשבה machshava rather than כוונה. We’ll see if that’s
relevant.
אמר ליה רבי אמי: Amar lei Rabbi Ami: ותיבעי ליה מעשה. ve-tiba'ei
lei ma'aseh. Why don’t you ask if they have an act, if
their acts are relevant? What does that mean? מאי שנא מעשה דלא
קא מיבעי ליה? mai shna ma'aseh d'lo ka miba'ei lei? You're not
asking that question about acts. דתנן: d'tenan: יש להם... yesh lahem... That
we have a mishna that says they have an act. We'll quote
the mishna in a minute. מחשבה נמי לא תיבעי ליה. Machshava nami
lo tibe'ei lei. You shouldn't ask about thoughts either; it should not
be a question.
דתנן—as dt'nan we taught in the
mishna. האלון והרמון והאגוז—you Ha-alun ve-ha-rimon ve-ha-egoz have these different types of
gourds and pomegranates and nuts and you want to hollow them out
and use them as bowls, as little bowls. And the question is
are they going to be considered a vessel to become מקבל טומאה.
mikabel tumah. For something to be a vessel it has to have
had intention to use it as a vessel. Now there are two
scenarios. One scenario is no physical act was done. I went and
I found a lovely piece of wood with a hollow in it
and I said, oh great, I'll use this as a bowl. The
other case is that I actually fashioned it to be a vessel
and I carved it. But in either case it requires the intention,
one just is the intention alone, the other is the intention that
accompanied an actual act to fashion it as a vessel. Okay so
here you have these various types of gourds and nuts or whatever
that were
חקקום תינוקות—that chakakum tinokes were hollowed out by תינוקות, tinokes, literally infants,
but it really means
minors. למוד בהן עפר—to La-mod ba-hen afar use to either measure dirt,
או שהתקינום לכף מאזנים—or o she-hitkinum le-kaf moznayim to use them for
a balance. So whatever it was, they were hollowed out to be
used as vessels. Does their act of making them into vessels, does
that constitute sufficiently halachically that they are now considered vessels? So the
halacha is טמאין. tme'in. They are טמא—meaning tamei they can become טמא,
tamei, they are considered vessels. מפני שיש להם מעשה—because Mi-pnei she-yesh lahem
ma'aseh they have an act, ואין להם מחשבה—but ve-ein lahem machshava they
do not have intention. Meaning if they walked by and saw a
hollowed out piece of wood and they said, oh I'm going to
go home and use this for my bowl, and they took it
home and they used it for their cereal bowl, that would not
make it a vessel. Then it's just their intention. But if they
actually are physically hollowing it out with that intention, that does make
it a vessel. So he says look you see that minors their
acts are significant, their thought divorced from their acts are not significant.
So what is your question? So we will find out the answer
tomorrow but I just want us to appreciate for a minute that
this is implicitly a critique on the point before I think about
not having כוונה. Because here it's saying an act is considered significant
and we do assume that the act is accompanied with a certain
type of an intent and is a meaningful act. So if they
can hollow out a gourd to make it into a vessel and
that's significant why can't they שחט shecht an animal with the intention
to do שחיטה? So this actually seems to be against the גמרא
we said earlier, says they do have acts when they're accompanied with
intent. We can assume that. Maybe they don't have intention when it
stands alone. So tomorrow we'll clarify exactly what the question is and
we'll see how the גמרא works to resolve it.